Guide to the A. Kenneth Pye, Chancellor, Records and Papers, 1960-1983 UA.06.51.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Chancellor of Duke University Records, 1976-1982
  - Subject Files, 1969-1983, bulk 1976-1982
    - Research Support, Office of, 1980-1982 (2 folders) (Box 27)
    - Research Triangle Institute, 1979-1980 (Box 27)
    - Residential Life (Federations), 1976-1979 (Box 27)
    - Retirement, 1977-1982 (3 folders) (Box 27)
    - Romance Languages, 1979-1982 (2 folders) (Box 27)
    - ROTC: Air Force, 1979-1981 (2 folders) (Box 27)
    - ROTC: Army, 1980-1982 (2 folders) (Box 27)
    - Round Table on Science and Public Affairs, 1976-1979 (Box 27)
    - S, 1976-1982 (2 folders) (Box 27)
    - S, 1981-1982 (Box 28)
    - Safety, Public Safety Department, 1976-1982 (2 folders) (Box 28)
    - Sanford, Terry (President), 1976-1982 (3 folders) (Box 28)
    - Saturday Review, 1979-1980 (Box 28)
    - Sawyer, Robert H., Director, Summer Educational Program, 1978-1979 (Box 28)
    - Sawyer, Dr. Robert N. (Talent Identification Program), 1981 (Box 28)
    - Seventies Review (Pye Report to Trustees), 1979 (Box 28)
    - Sociology Department, 1976-1982 (2 folders) (Box 28)
    - South-East Consortium for International Development, 1981-1982 (Box 28)
    - Special Events, 1981 (Box 28)
    - Spengler, Joseph J., 1976-1980 (Box 28)
    - Sponsored Programs, 1981 (Box 28)
    - Staff Employees, 1982 (Box 28)
    - Student Affairs, Office of, 1978-1982 (2 folders) (Box 28)
    - Student Health, 1976-1981 (2 folders) (Box 28)
    - Student Health, Task Force on, 1978-1979 (Box 28)
    - Students (Associated Students of Duke University), 1976-1982 (3 folders) (Box 28)
    - Students: Employment, 1976-1978 (Box 28)
    - Students: Federations (Report of the Task Force on Federations), 1982 (Box 28)
    - Students: Freshmen, 1976-1978 (Box 28)
    - Students: Miscellaneous (Questions by Students for Sanford), 1977-1979 (Box 28)
    - Students: Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1981 (Box 28)
    - Study Abroad Program (Includes Statistics), 1977-1979 (Box 28)
    - Study Abroad Program, 1980-1981 (Box 28)
    - Summer Performing Arts, 1976-1979, 1981 (2 folders) (Box 28)
    - Summer Session, 1976-1982 (2 folders) (Box 29)
    - Summer Transitional Program, 1978-1981 (2 folders) (Box 29)
    - Summer Utilization of University Facilities, 1976 (Box 29)
    - Sutherland, Asbill, and Brennan, 1977 (Box 29)
    - T, 1980-1982 (Box 29)
    - TelCom, 1976-1982 (2 folders) (Box 29)
    - Ten Universities Group, 1979-1981 (2 folders) (Box 29)
    - TIAA-CREF, 1979-1981 (2 folders) (Box 29)
    - TIP (Talent Identification Program, Robert N. Sawyer), 1980-1982 (Box 29)
    - Traffic and Parking, 1976-1982 (2 folders) (Box 29)
    - Translation Services, 1976-1982 (2 folders) (Box 29)
    - Triangle Universities Center for Advanced Studies, 1975-1980 (Box 29)
    - Triangle Universities Computation Center (TUCC), 1976-1979 (Box 29)
    - Organization for Tropical Studies, 1976 (Box 29)
    - Tuition and Fees, 1977-1981 (2 folders) (Box 29)
    - U, (Rosati Endowment Fund), 1978-1979 (Box 29)
    - Undergraduate Research Participation Program, United Negro College Fund, 1979-1981 (2 folders) (Box 29)
    - University Center, 1976-1982 (2 folders) (Box 29)
    - University Relations (see William Green for prior years), 1978-1982 (2 folders) (Box 29)
    - University Research Council, 1976-1982 (2 folders) (Box 29)
    - University Union, 1976-1979 (Box 30)
    - Urban Observatory, 1976-1978 (Box 30)
    - V, 1977-1980 (Box 30)
    - V-W, 1980-1982 (Box 30)
    - W, 1978-1980 (Box 30)
    - Wage and Price Controls, 1978-1979 (Box 30)
    - Wage and Salary Administration, 1976-1981 (3 folders) (Box 30)
    - Ward, James A., University Architect, 1976-1982 (2 folders) (Box 30)
    - Wardropper Report ("Climate for Liberal Learning", includes students responses to report), 1980 (Box 30)
    - WDBS, 1977-1980 (2 folders) (Box 30)
    - White, Colonel Van R. (Chinese Art Collection), 1977 (Box 30)
    - X-Rated Films, 1977 (Box 30)
    - Y (Yale), 1978-1980 (Box 30)
    - Y-Z, 1980-1982 (Box 30)
    - Zoology Department, 1979-1981 (2 folders) (Box 30)
    - Zu'Bi, Mr. Hatim S., 1977-1978 (Box 30)
  - Medical Center Subject Files, 1972-1982 (bulk 1976-1982)
    This subseries consists of subject files created during Pye's second tenure as Chancellor, 1976-1982, related to the Duke University Medical Center. Major subjects include Highland Hospital (Asheville, NC), the School of Nursing, and retrenchment. William G. Anlyan, Vice President for Health Affairs, is the primary correspondent within the series.
    - Advisory Committee, 1978-1980 (Box 30)
    - Anlyan, Dr. William G., 1972-1982 (5 folders) (Box 30)
    - Budget, 1980 (Box 30)
    - Busse, Dr. Ewald W., 1977-1980 (Box 30)
    - Children's Celebrity Golf Classic, 1977-1980 (Box 30)
    - Department of Community Health Sciences (Dr. Estes), 1977-1979 (Box 30)
    - Department of Community Health Sciences (King's Fund Exchange), 1981 (Box 30)
    - Department of Health Administration, 1976-1979 (Box 30)
    - Development (John S. Thomas), 1977-1980 (Box 30)
    - Development, 1980-1982 (Box 30)
    - Duke Hospital, 1978-1982 (2 folders) (Box 30)
    - Duke Hospital North, 1980-1982 (2 folders) (Box 31)
    - Duke University Hospital Advisory Board, 1979 (Box 31)
    - Foreign Students Admissions, 1977 (Box 31)
    - Highland Hospital, 1976-1982 (Box 31)
    - Laboratory Animal Resources Division: Task Force, 1978 (Box 31)
    - Medical Center Layoffs, 1982 (Box 31)
    - Medicare/Medicaid, 1981-1982 (Box 31)
    - Miscellaneous, 1976-1982 (5 folders) (Box 31)
    - Nursing Education Task Force: Minutes, 1981 (Box 31)
    - Nursing School, 1978-1982 (4 folders) (Box 31)
    - PDC: Private Diagnostic Clinic, 1976-1982 (3 folders) (Box 31)
    - The Private Sector in Medical Care and Education, 1977-1982 (2 folders) (Box 31)
    - Robinson, Dr. Roscoe, 1976-1980 (Box 32)
    - Sea Level Hospital, 1977-1981 (Box 32)
    - Shytle, John, 1977-1979 (Box 32)
    - Tenure, 1980-1981 (Box 32)
    - Trustees: Medical Center Affairs Committee, 1978 Dec. 7-1982 Feb. 26 (10 folders) (Box 32)
    - Wallace, Dr. Andrew G., 1981-1982 (Box 32)
    - Whitehead Institute, 1973-1981 (2 folders) (Box 32)
  - Committee Files, 1971-1983, bulk 1976-1982
    This subseries consists of committee files created during Pye's second tenure as Chancellor, 1976-1982. The files are arranged into two sub-series: files regarding various standing committees and ad hoc committees are followed by files pertaining to planning committees and the University Long-Range Planning Committee. Other committees represented include the Athletic Council, Committee on the Social Implications of Duke's Investment Policies, search committees for a provost and a Vice-Chancellor for Data Processing, and the Undergraduate Faculty Council in the Arts and Sciences (UFCAS) Committee on Financial Aid and Admissions. Information assembled by the Long-Range Planning Committee and it various taskforces was used in two planning documents written by Pye: Planning for the Eighties (1978) and Directions for Progress (1980). Directions for Progress proposed reorganization in the School of Forestry and Environmental Studies and discontinuing the School of Nursing and the Department of Education. Other subjects include financial aid and admissions, instruction in the arts, the Department of Education, residential life, cooperative programs, the marine laboratory, and the Department of Sociology. Major correspondents include Bruce Wardropper, H. Keith H. Brodie, William Bevan, and Jean O'Barr.
    - Ad Hoc and Standing Committees, 1971-1983
      - Athletic Council, 1971-1982 (3 folders) (Box 32)
      - Chancellor's Committee on Wage and Salary, 1978-1979 (3 folders) (Box 32)
      - Committee on the Social Implication of Duke's Investment Policies, 1972-1981 (2 folders) (Box 32)
      - Educational Facilities Committee, 1977-1982 (3 folders) (Box 32)
      - Environmental Concerns Committee, 1977-1982 (Box 33)
      - Faculty Hearing Committee, 1974-1978 (Box 33)
      - Committee on Hunger, 1979-1980 (Box 33)
      - Library Council, 1976-1980 (Box 33)
      - President's Special Advisory Search Committee, 1979-1981 (Box 33)
      - Provost Search Committee, 1982-1983 (2 folders) (Box 33)
      - Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences (UFCAS), 1977-1982 (Box 33)
      - UFCAS: Committee on Admissions and Financial Aid, 1978-1981 (3 folders) (Box 33)
      - UFCAS: Curriculum Committee, 1978-1982 (Box 33)
      - UFCAS: Special Committee on Educational Policy and Program in Trinity College (Minutes), 1978-1980 (2 folders) (Box 33)
      - University Review Committee on the Use of Human Subjects in Non-Medical Research, 1973-1981 (Box 33)
      - Vice-Chancellor for Data Processing Search Committee, 1982-1982 (2 folders) (Box 33)
    - Planning Committees, 1965-1981
      - Admissions, Financial Aid, and Tuition-Advisory Committee, 1979-1980 (Box 34)
      - Arts: Chancellor's Advisory Committee, 1979-1980 (Box 34)
      - ASDU Resolutions, 1980 (Box 34)
      - Cooperative Programs: Chancellor's Advisory Committee, 1979-1980 (6 folders) (Box 34)
      - Department of Education, 1979-1981 (Box 34)
      - Department of Education: Responses, 1980-1981 (Box 34)
      - Department of Health, Physical Education and Recreation, 1974-1980 (Box 34)
      - Directions for Progress (Includes Responses), 1980-1981 (2 folders) (Box 34)
      - Directions for Progress: News Releases, 1980 (Box 34)
      - Incentives for Faculty Outside Fundraising and Overhead Reimbursement Policy, 1979-1980 (Box 34)
      - Institutional Advancement and Alumni Affairs: Chancellor's Committee, 1979-1981 (Box 34)
      - Marine Laboratory, 1976-1979 (Box 34)
      - Marine Laboratory: Responses to Planning for the Eighties, 1979-1980 (Box 34)
      - Planning Documents from other Universities, 1973-1980 (Box 34)
      - Planning for the Eighties (Includes Responses), 1978-1980 (Box 34)
      - Planning: General Correspondence, 1965-1980 (Box 34)
      - School of Forestry, 1977-1979 (2 folders) (Box 34)
      - School of Nursing, 1978-1982 (4 folders) (Box 35)
      - School of Nursing: Class Agents, 1979-1980 (Box 35)
      - School of Nursing: Self-Study Report, 1978 (Box 35)
      - Sociology Department, 1979-1980 (Box 35)
      - Student Affairs: Chancellor's Advisory Committee, 1979-1980 (Box 35)
      - Task Force on the Future of Undergraduate Residential Life, 1979-1980 (2 folders) (Box 35)
      - Task Force on the Future of Undergraduate Residential Life: Appendices 1, 2, and 3, 1979-1980 (Box 35)
      - Task Force on the Future of Residential Life: Appendix 4, 1980 (Box 35)
      - Task Force on Academic Space Utilization, 1979-1981 (Box 35)
      - Task Force on Upward Mobility, 1979-1980 (Box 35)
      - University Long-Range Planning Committee, 1976-1980 (4 folders) (Box 35)
      - University Long-Range Planning Committee: Year-Round Operations: Task Force, 1979-1980 (Box 35)
  - Assistants to the Chancellor Files, 1968-1980, bulk 1976-1980, and undated
    This subseries consists of files created during Pye's second tenure as Chancellor, 1976-1982, by staff assistants in the Chancellor's office, chiefly Gail Hagel and Jennifer Hillman. The files consist chiefly of information gathered in relation to long-range planning, including questionnaires, communications with members of the Long-Range Planning Committee, statistical data, and other materials.
    - Subject Files, 1969-1980
      - Academic Affairs, 1978-1979 (Box 36)
      - Advanced Placement Study, 1979 Sept. (Box 36)
      - Alumni Affairs: Planning, 1973-1976 (Box 36)
      - Associated Students of Duke University (ASDU), 1976 (Box 36)
      - Trustee Roles and Responsibilities, 1978 (2 folders) (Box 36)
      - Career Resources Committee, 1976-1980 (Box 36)
      - Counseling and Psychological Services (CAPS), Commonwealth Studies Center, 1974-1976 (5 folders) (Box 36)
      - Continuing Education, 1976-1977 (Box 36)
      - Dual Careers, 1979-1980 (Box 36)
      - East-West Expressway, 1978 (Box 36)
      - Emergency Plan, 1970-1975 (Box 36)
      - Employee Audits, 1977-1979 (Box 36)
      - Energy Conservation Committee, 1977 (Box 36)
      - Equal Opportunity Office, 1976-1977 (Box 36)
      - Federal Regulations in Higher Education, 1976-1978 (Box 36)
      - Health Education Program, 1976-1979 (Box 36)
      - Honor Code, 1979 (Box 36)
      - International Studies and Study Abroad, 1974-1977 (Box 36)
      - International Studies and Study Abroad, 1977-1978 (Box 37)
      - Internships, 1971-1977 (Box 37)
      - Judicial Board, circa 1971-1979 (Box 37)
      - Luncheon Program, 1978-1980 (Box 37)
      - Medical Center Committee for Clinical Investigations, 1972-1973 (Box 37)
      - Physical Education-Recreation Task Force, 1973-1974 (Box 37)
      - Pickets and Protest Policy, 1975 (Box 37)
      - Race Relations, 1976-1980 (Box 37)
      - Residential Life Committee, 1972-1974 (Box 37)
      - Stanford University-Duke University Study, 1976-1979 (Box 37)
      - State of Education, 1979-1980 (Box 37)
      - Student Counseling Services, 1976-1978 (2 folders) (Box 37)
      - Student Counseling Services Committee, 1977-1978 (Box 37)
      - Student Health Advisory Committee, 1975-1979 (Box 37)
      - Summer Session Advisory Committee, 1969-1971 (Box 37)
      - Task Force on Student Health, 1978-1979 (Box 37)
      - Tenure Study, 1975-1977 (Box 37)
      - University Budget Committee, October, 1975 (Box 37)
      - University Committee on Clinical Investigations, 1973-1974 (Box 37)
      - University Faculty, 1976 (Box 37)
      - University Union Board, 1971-1974 (Box 37)
      - Writing Center, 1977 (Box 37)
      - Writing Proposal, 1977 (Box 37)
    - Long Range Planning, 1968-1980 and undated
      - Planning Studies: Appendices, Department of Education, 1979 (Box 37)
      - Planning Studies: Appendices, Department of Sociology, 1973-1979 (Box 37)
      - Planning Studies: Appendices, Marine Laboratory, 1976-1979 (Box 37)
      - Planning Studies: Appendices, School of Forestry and Environmental Studies, 1977-1979 (Box 37)
      - Planning Studies: Appendices, School of Nursing, 1972-1979 (Box 37)
      - Planning Studies: Arts and Sciences Departments, 1971-1978 (Box 37)
      - Planning Studies: Departmental and Program Evaluation Questionnaire, 1976 (3 folders) (Box 37)
      - Planning Studies: Departmental Evaluation, 1976-1977 (2 folders) (Box 37)
      - Planning Studies: Departmental Evaluations, Charts, and Stats, 1970-1977 (Box 37)
      - Planning Studies: Duke University Athletic Association, 1976 (Box 38)
      - Planning Studies: DU Bus. and Fin. Comm., FY 76/77 through 1977 Apr. 3, Proposed Budget, 1977-1978 (Box 38)
      - Planning Studies: DU Bus. and Fin. Comm. Operations through 1978 Nov., 3 yr. Forecast; Least Cost Routing Proposal (Box 38)
      - Planning Studies: DU Bus. and Fin. Comm. Operations through 1978 Dec. (Box 38)
      - Planning Studies: DU Bus. and Fin. Comm. Operations through 1979 Apr. (Box 38)
      - Planning Studies: DU Bus. and Fin. Comm. Operations through Year Ending 1979 June (Box 38)
      - Planning Studies: DU Bus. and Fin. Comm. Operations through 11/79, Forecast, 1980 (Box 38)
      - Planning Studies: Faculty Evaluation, 1976-1978 (Box 38)
      - Planning Studies: Faculty Statistics, 1976 (Box 38)
      - Planning Studies: General Statistics, 1977 (Box 38)
      - Planning Studies: Graduate School Statistics, 1976 (Box 38)
      - Planning Studies: GRE and GPA Information, 1975-1976 (Box 38)
      - Planning Studies: Long-Range Planning, 1977 (Box 38)
      - Planning Studies: Long-Range Planning Committee, Perkins Library System, Final Report, 1978 (Box 38)
      - Planning Studies: Long-Range Planning Committee, 1968-1978 (Box 38)
      - Planning Studies: NC Association of Independent Colleges and Universities, Annual Report, 1979 (Box 38)
      - Planning Studies: Positive Employee Actions, 1977-1978 (Box 38)
      - Planning Studies: Pre-College Evaluation, 1978 (Box 38)
      - Planning Studies: Program Evaluations, 1976 (Box 38)
      - Planning Studies: Publications Board Study Committee, 1970-1971 (Box 38)
      - Planning Studies: Questionnaire, 1976 (Box 38)
      - Planning Studies: Report of Special Comm. on Functions & Organization of the Board of Trustees, 1969 (Box 38)
      - Planning Studies: Report of Special Comm. on Functions and Organization of Board of Trustees - Appendices, 1969 (Box 38)
      - Planning Studies: School of Law, 1975-1976 (Box 38)
      - Planning Studies: Summary Report of the University Planning Committee, 1972 Oct. (Box 38)
      - Planning Studies: Teaching Education at Duke University, 1979 (Box 38)
      - Planning Studies: Undergraduate Statistics and General Others, 1975-1979 (Box 38)
      - Planning Studies: Accelerated Curriculum, 1977-1980 (Box 39)
      - Planning Studies: Admissions, 1977-1980 (Box 39)
      - Planning Studies: Arts, 1970-1980 (3 folders) (Box 39)
      - Planning Studies: Chancellor's Committee on Cooperative Programs, 1978-1979 (2 folders) (Box 39)
      - Planning Studies: Chancellor's Advisory Comm. on Incentives for Faculty Outside Fundraising, 1977-1980 (Box 39)
      - Planning Studies: Department Summaries, 1976 and undated (Box 39)
      - Planning Studies: Faculty Statistics, circa 1979 (Box 39)
      - Planning Studies: Financial Aid, 1972-1979 (2 folders) (Box 39)
      - Planning Studies: Long-Range Planning - Correspondence, 1976-1978 (Box 39)
      - Planning Studies: School of Nursing - Letters, 1980 (Box 39)
      - Planning Studies: Residential Life, 1969-1980 (Box 39)
      - Planning Studies: Residential Life Task Force - Report, 1979-1980 (Box 39)
      - Planning Studies: Student Affairs, 1969-1980 (Box 39)
      - Planning Studies: Year Around Operation, 1979-1980 and undated (Box 39)
      - Planning Studies: Miscellaneous, 1979-1980 and undated (Box 39)
- Chancellor of Duke University Records, 1970-1971, 1976- 1982
  This series contains restricted materials from each of Pye's chancellorships. For further information, contact University Archives staff.
  - Restricted Files (Box 40)
- A. Kenneth Pye Papers, 1968-1976, undated
  This series includes typescripts of speeches, correspondence, reports, and other material created during Pye's tenure as Dean of the School of Law, Chancellor, and University Counsel. The papers reflect matters outside of Duke University. The correspondence, spanning 1968 to 1974, includes letter from Pye's former law students and gives details about their careers and lives. Pye's responses are included. The correspondence further reflects Pye's work as an attorney and an educator, as it in part pertains to legal questions and issues. North Carolina Senator Sam Ervin and Chief Justice Warren Burger are among those who consulted with Pye on legal matters. The speeches and addresses, which are dated from 1968 to 1974, were primarily delivered at other institutions and relate to legal education and legal issues, including student demonstrations. Several subject files include reports and materials on university matters, including a public hearing on the ROTC, a 1975 report on teacher education at Duke, and reports from the Durham Urban Observatory, a joint research project between Duke, North Carolina Central University, and the city of Durham.
  - Correspondence, 1968-1974 (Box 41)
  - Speeches, 1968-1974 and undated
    - Dean's Workshop Speech and Miscellanea, circa 1971-1979 (Box 41)
    - Hatcher Lecture, Mercer University, 1976 Feb. 2 (Box 41)
    - Higher Education Speech on Carnegie Commission (includes Pye, "Meeting the Needs for Legal Education in the South"), 1975 (Box 41)
    - Law Day Speech, circa 1971-1979 (Box 41)
    - Speeches, 1967-1970 (Box 41)
    - Speeches, 1971-1973 (Box 41)
    - Speeches, 1974-1975 (Box 41)
    - Speeches, undated (Box 41)
  - Subject Files,1970-1976 and undated
    - Durham Urban Observatory Reports, 1976 (Box 41)
    - Medical Center Board of Visitors, 1969-1971 and undated
      - Education: Dr. Kinney 1970 (Box 41)
      - Management: Mr. Steinert, 1969-1970 and undated (Box 41)
      - Hospital: Dr. Sessions, 1970 (Box 41)
      - General Progress Report: Dr. Anlyan, 1970 (Box 41)
      - Education: Dean Jacobansky, 1970 and undated (Box 41)
      - Facilities: Dr. Elchlepp, 1969-1971 and undated (Box 41)
    - National Labor Relations Board (Duke vs. Local 77 and Local 1199D), circa 1972 (Box 41)
    - ROTC Hearings (Notes and Information), 1971 Mar. (Box 41)
    - Teacher Education at Duke University, 1975 (Box 41)
    - Finances of the School of Law (Box 41)
    - Medical Center Administration, 1972-73 Budget Request (Box 41)
    - Report on the Financing of Intercollegiate Athletics (Box 41)
    - School of Medicine, 1972-73 Budget Request (Box 41)
- Oversized Material
  This series contains oversize materials from each of Pye's chancellorships. Included are a Duke University Athletic Association Long Range Plan (1971), Duke University Hospital Long Range Forecast, and information regarding budgets, tuition, and fees. For further information, contact University Archives staff.